Guide to the Herbert Clarence Bradshaw Papers, 1922-1976 RL.00143
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Herbert Clarence Bradshaw papers
1922-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence, 1908-1976
RL.00143
35 Linear Feet
Approximately 39,585 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Herbert Clarence Bradshaw were acquired by Duke University as gifts, 1977-1987.
Biographical Note
Herbert Clarence Bradshaw (1908-1976), a Democrat, Baptist, author-historian, journalist, churchman, educator and civic leader in both Virginia and North Carolina, was born Nov. 7, 1908, in Rice, Prince Edward County, Va. He attended Hampden-Sydney College (B.A., 1930), and the University of Virginia (M.A., 1933 in classical languages), and was awarded a Litt.D. degree from Hampden-Sydney in 1967. For twenty years he taught and served as a principal in Virginia schools. He began a full-time journalism career as Sunday Feature Editor of the Durham Morning Herald and became editor of the editorial page from 1964 until retirement in 1974.
Bradshaw is author of The History of Prince Edward County, Virginia (1955), History of Hampden-Sydney College, Vol. I (1976), History of Farmville, Va. (1948), Toward the Dawn: History of the First Quarter-Century of the N.C. State Association for the Blind, 1934-1960 (1961), and fifty articles from 1935 to 1976 on the histories of the Baptist Church, the Lions organization, the blind organizations in N.C., and historical pieces on such topics as Patrick Henry, Thomas Jefferson, and historic houses.
Collection Overview
Bradshaw's papers show detailed involvement as a member of the N.C. State Commission for the Blind for 18 years; member, Advisory Board, Mary Duke Biddle Art Gallery for the Blind in the N C Museum of Art, Raleigh; and President of the N. C Society for the Prevention of Blindness.
Many printed items - rosters, programs, clippings, and photographs - are scattered throughout the files where they are integral parts of personal or organizational files. Papers on Durham include histories and correspondence on city and county government (1853-1973), Chamber of Commerce, Civitan and Optimist Clubs, Merchants Association, Public Library, and the School Board. The latter includes a substantial sequence of folders on Durham, N.C. race relations issues and school integration. There are printed programs of cultural events held in Richmond, Durham, and Raleigh, 1929-1972. The papers include programs, rosters, histories, minutes and correspondence on Lions Club activities in Durham and throughout N.C., 1922-1974.
Material prepared for the Durham (N.C.) Morning Herald centennial edition includes the histories of local organizations, 1805-1953. Bradshaw kept detailed diaries and correspondence on his Book Page and his editorials, 1949-1973. Important in Civil War histories is Bradshaw's account of historic events in the Appomattox area which he wrote for the Centennial Edition of the Farmville (Va.) Herald, 1965. A longer local history account appears in that newspaper's Sesquicentennial Edition of 1948.
Duke University Professor Mason Crum's unpublished manuscript, Washington Duke, is included in the Duke University section (Box 31) along with Bradshaw's 1949-1973 correspondence with Duke faculty. Dr. J. B. Rhine's correspondence shows the development at Duke of his Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man, 1963-1972.
The collection contains voluminous correspondence from 1922 to 1976 (Boxes 19-27), including 44 years of farm business papers on the 900-acre farm in Virginia he and his brother managed. The correspondence also includes the writing of the history of the Baptist Church in N.C., 1805-1973. There is correspondence also on the Yates Baptist Association and the Watts Street Baptist Church, 1950-1971. Other files of correspondence relate to his forty-four year involvement with Hampden-Sydney College (Box 42). Bradshaw's interest in genealogy led to lengthy correspondence on genealogies of the Armistead, Bradshaw, Cunningham, Chambliss, Few, Fuqua, Lockett, McGehee, Marshall, Nash, Scarborough, Venable, and Walton families. Included is a morgue of hundreds of glossy photographs of contemporary writers. There are letters signed by William O. Douglas; Dean Acheson; Dean Rusk; William P. Rogers; J. William Fulbright; Governors Luther Hodges, Terry Sanford and Robert Scott; Senators Henry Jackson and B. Everett Jordan; Norman Mailer; J. B. Rhine; and Douglas M. Knight. There is correspondence with Myrta Lockett Avary, author of A Virginia Girl in the Civil War, and her memoirs are included.
Addition (87-94) contains correspondence, notes and printed material for the development of Durham and its commemoration of the U.S. Bicentennial, 1976. Also contains information concerning health care in N.C., and notes from various conferences held by the U.S. State department for news editors.
Other parts of Bradshaw's papers are also held by the Virginia Baptist Historical Society at the University of Richmond and the Virginia State Library.
Baptists -- North Carolina -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Segregation in education -- Durham (N.C.); Blind -- Services for -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Duke University; Hampden-Sydney College; Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence, 1908-1976
- Biographical and Autobiographical Information
  Scope and Contents note
  This information is filed in the first box of the collection. It includes a vita, letters, articles, awards, clippings, a formal photograph, and other items. Box 1 also contains an inventory of the collection and the Virginia State Library inventory.
- Alphabetical Files
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, 1927-1929, 1950-1955, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Avary, Myrta Lockett: 1846, 1866, 1903, 1933, 1940-1946 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Legal Documents (Box 2)
    - Memoirs (undated) (Box 2)
    - Photos (Box 2)
    - Poetry (Box 2)
    - Writings (Box 2)
    - Sherwin article on Avary (Box 2)
  - Baptist Church, North Carolina: (Box 3)
    - Baptist Church Histories 1930, 1935-1973 (Box 3)
    - Baptist State Convention of N.C. 1960, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Churches of Durham 1805-1951 1952-1968, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - First Baptist Church, Durham 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Greater Durham Evangelistic Crusade 1965 (Box 3)
    - Religion - Articles, news clippings, etc. 1859, 1930, 1954-1973 (Box 3)
    - Watts Street Baptist Church 1950-1970 (Box 4)
    - Yates Baptist Association 1953-1971 (Box 5)
  - Blindness:
    - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness 1964-1973 (Box 6-7)
    - N.C. Association for the Blind 1948-1974 (Box 8)
    - N.C. Association for the Blind 1960-1967 (Box 9)
    - Glaucoma Clinics (Box 9)
    - N.C. Association for the Blind 1947, 1956-1973 (Box 9)
      - The White Cane (Box 9)
    - N.C. Eye and Human Tissue Bank 1960-1971 (Box 9)
    - N.C. Society for the Prevention of Blindness 1966-1974 (Box 10)
    - N.C. State Association for the Blind 1934-1960 (Box 11)
      - Toward the Dawn: History of the N.C. State Association for the Blind (Box 11)
    - N.C. State Commission for the Blind 1943, 1948-1973 (Box 12-16)
      - Biennial Reports 1950-1968 (Box 12-16)
      - Manual (Box 12-16)
      - Publications (Box 12-16)
      - Vocational Rehabilitation Plan (Box 12-16)
    - N.C. State Commission for the Blind and N.C. Bureau of Employment for the Blind: (Box 17-18)
      - Quarterly Reports 1964-1970 (Box 17-18)
    - The Seeing Eye, Inc. 1957-1958 (Box 18)
  - Book Reviews Scrapbook (Bradshaw's) (see at end of Papers) 1931-1945 (Box 18)
  - Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence:
    - Book Reviews Scrapbook 1931-1945 (Box 69)
    - Personal and Family Clippings and Memorabilia 1952-1974 (Box 19)
    - Personal and Family Correspondence (Farm) 1929-1973 (Box 20-22)
    - Personal and Family Correspondence (General) 1922-1975, undated (Box 23-26)
    - Speaking Engagements 1956-1973 (Box 27)
    - Writings 1935-1976 (Box 28-29)
  - Campbell College, Buie's Creek, N.C.
    - Graham A. Barden Chair of Government (See N.C. Campbell College) (Box 28-29)
  - Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission (See N.C. Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission) (Box 28-29)
  - Civil War: (Box 30)
    - Bennitt Place 1962-1964 (Box 30)
    - Civil War Centennial Commission 1958-1965 (Box 30)
    - Confederate Veterans Reunions 1929, 1932 (Box 30)
    - Farmville Herald Centennial 1965 (Box 30)
    - Farmville Herald Sesquicentennial 1948 (Box 30)
    - Fortifications at High Bridge, Appomattox River 1865 (Box 30)
    - Johnston, Joseph E., General 1959-1963 (Box 30)
    - N.C. Confederate Centennial Commission 1958-1965 (Box 30)
    - Tell Ma to send me some meat to boil with peas. Soldier's Letter. Apr. 1864 (Box 30)
  - Duke University: (Box 31)
    - Bradshaw's Correspondence with Duke Faculty 1949-1973 (Box 31)
    - General Telephone Issue 1972 (Box 31)
    - Rhine's Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man 1963-1972 (Box 31)
    - Rule of Law Research Center. Arthur Larson 1960, 1966 (Box 31)
    - Sanford, Terry 1962, 1964, 1970-1972 (Box 31)
    - Washington Duke by Mason Crum ca. 1951 (Box 31)
  - Durham: (Box 32)
    - Chamber of Commerce 1961-1973 (Box 32)
    - City and County Government 1853-1953, 1957-1973 (Box 32)
    - Civitan and Optimist Clubs 1952 (Box 32)
    - County Association for the Blind 1949-1959 (Box 32)
    - Golden Age Society 1956 (Box 32)
    - Merchants Association 1956, 1969-1972 (Box 32)
    - N.C. College at Durham 1950-1952, 1968 (Box 32)
    - 1963 - All-America City Award 1963 (Box 32)
    - Public Library 1897-1936, 1953-1961 (Box 32)
    - Research Triangle, History of 1953-1965 (Box 32)
    - Scarborough Nursery School 1950 (Box 32)
    - School Board 1951, 1965-1966 (Box 32)
    - School Study Committee 1959-1960 (Box 32)
    - Social Scene 1960-1963, 1965 (Box 32)
    - United Fund Campaign 1962-1973 (Box 32)
  - Durham (N.C.) Morning Herald:
    - Book Page 1949, 1955-1973 (Box 33)
    - Book Page. Correspondence 1950-1973 (Box 33)
    - Book Reviews by Bradshaw 1931-1945 (Box 69)
    - Centennial Edition. Correspondence 1953 (Box 34)
    - Centennial Edition, Histories of Organizations 1805-1953 (Box 34)
    - Diaries of Book Reviews and Editorials 1951-1972 (Box 35-36)
    - Editorial Background Material 1929-1973 (Box 37-39)
    - Editorials 1960-1967 (Box 39)
    - Editorials. Correspondence 1949-1973 (Box 40)
    - Editorials by Bradshaw 1961-1963 (Box 39)
    - Features. Correspondence 1953-1958, 1973 (Box 34)
    - Frank S. Hickman's Just a Minute Column 1952-1964 (Box 34)
    - Monthly Bulletins 1950-1973 (Box 34)
    - Personnel Directories 1954-1973 (Box 34)
    - Style Book 1949 (Box 34)
  - Eggleston, Joseph DuPuy - McAllister, James Gray (See Hampden-Sydney Correspondence. Eggleston, Joseph DuPuy - McAllister, James Gray Correspondence) 1929-1956 (Box 34)
  - Genealogies: (Box 41)
    - Anderson (Box 41)
    - Armistead (Box 41)
    - Bradshaw (Box 41)
    - Carrington (Box 41)
    - Chambliss (Box 41)
    - Cunningham (Box 41)
    - Davis (Box 41)
    - Fain (Box 41)
    - Few (Box 41)
    - Flippen (Box 41)
    - Fuqua (Box 41)
    - Goodrich (Box 41)
    - Holcombe (Box 41)
    - Jenkins (Box 41)
    - Kennon (Box 41)
    - Kerr (Box 41)
    - Ligon (Box 41)
    - Lockett (Box 41)
    - McGehee (Box 41)
    - Marshall (Box 41)
    - Nash (Box 41)
    - Osborne (Box 41)
    - Pallmore (Box 41)
    - Pankey (Box 41)
    - Scarborough (Box 41)
    - Thomson (Box 41)
    - Townes (Box 41)
    - Venable (Box 41)
    - Walker (Box 41)
    - Walthall (Box 41)
    - Walton (Box 41)
    - White (Box 41)
    - Wimbish (Box 41)
    - Woodson (Box 41)
  - Hampden-Sidney 1927-1973 (Box 42)
  - Hampden-Sidney. Bradshaw's Correspondence 1927-1973 (Box 42)
    - Eggleston, Joseph DuPuy - McAllister, James Gray Correspondence 1929-1956 (Box 42)
  - Historical Book Club of N.C., Greensboro, N.C. Annual Town Meeting on Books (See N.C. Historical Book Club) (Box 42)
  - Hospitals. North Carolina (See Public Health) (Box 42)
  - Human Betterment League of N.C. (See N.C. 1947-1976 Human Betterment League) (Box 42)
  - Lions:
    - Apex to Zebulon 1969-1972 (Box 43)
    - Conventions, National 1960, 1970-1973 (Box 44)
    - Conventions, State (N.C.) 1961-1973 (Box 44)
    - District Governors 1960-1972 (Box 45-46)
    - District 31G 1960-1974 (Box 47)
    - Durham 1950-1973 (Box 48-49)
    - History of Lionism 1922-1960 (Box 50)
    - International 1951-1952, 1966-1973 (Box 50)
    - International. Candidates for Director 1970-1972 (Box 50)
    - International. Constitution and By-laws Committee 1970-1972 (Box 50)
    - International. Politics 1969-1970 (Box 50)
    - State Council 1968-1973 (Box 51)
    - Zone Chairman 1967-1970 (Box 51)
    - Zone Club Reports 1967-1970 (Box 51)
  - Lockett Genealogical Chart (Box 69)
  - Mary Duke Biddle Gallery for the Blind, N.C. Museum of Art, Raleigh, N.C. (See N.C. Mary Duke Biddle Gallery for the Blind, N.C. Museum of Art, Raleigh, N.C.) (Box 69)
  - National Foreign Policy Conference for Editors and Broadcasters. Washington, D. C. 1964, 1970, 1972 (Box 52)
  - National Health Council (See Public Health) (Box 52)
  - National Policy and Performance Council 1968-1972 (See U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. National Policy and Performance Council) (Box 52)
  - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness (See Blindness: National Society for the Prevention of Blindness) (Box 52)
  - North Carolina:
    - N.C. Advisory Council to the Peace Corps 1962-1964 (Box 53)
    - N.C. American Revolution Bicentennial Committee 1971-1973 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Awards 1966-1967, 1971 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Bowles for Governor 1972 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Campbell College, Buies Creek, 1962, 1967-1968, 1973 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Graham A. Barden Chair of Government (Box 53)
    - N.C. Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission 1961-1963 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Council on World Affairs 1959-1963 (Box 53)
    - N.C. Democratic Party. Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner. Raleigh, N.C.1963 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Fund 1966 (Box 54)
    - N.C. General Assembly, 1969. Interest Rate Study Commission 1969-1973 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Governor's Conference on Planning for Higher Education. Raleigh, N.C. 1968 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Governor's Conference, Richmond, Va. Official Celebration of the 200th Anniversary of the Birth of George Washington 1932 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Governor's Study Committee on Structure and Organization of Higher Education. Raleigh, N.C. 1971 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Historical Book Club, Greensboro, N.C. Annual Town Meeting on Books 1961-1971 (Box 54)
    - N.C. Huguenot Society 1953-1972 (Box 55)
    - N.C. Human Betterment League 1947-1976 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Literary and Historical Association 1963-1972 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Mary Duke Biddle Gallery for the Blind, N.C. Museum of Art, Raleigh, N.C. 1966-1969, 1972 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Political Campaigns 1972 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Rehabilitation Association 1966-1967 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Salem Academy 1969-1970 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Society Sons of the American Revolution 1956-1971 (Box 56)
    - N.C. Study in Vocational Rehabilitation 1965-1969 (Box 57)
    - N.C. Wake County Courthouse Speech. Professor Albert Coates Sept. 13, 1970 (Box 57)
  - Photographs:
    - List of Photographs (Box 58)
    - Buildings, places, scenes (Box 58)
    - Genre (Box 58)
    - People (Box 58-59)
    - Transportation (Box 59)
  - Political Campaigns (North Carolina). (See N.C. Political Campaigns) 1972 (Box 59)
  - President Nixon's Proclamation: Save your Vision Week, 1973 1973 (Box 69)
  - Press Associations:
    - American Press Institute Seminar 1967 (Box 60)
    - Press Associations 1929-1963 (Box 60)
    - Southern Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation Seminars for Southern Journalists 1967-1972 (Box 61)
    - Southern Regional Education Board, Seminars for Southern Journalists 1966-1968 (Box 62)
  - Public Health:
    - Durham County TB and Health Association 1952, 1954-1957 (Box 63)
    - Hospitals. North Carolina 1965-1972 (Box 63)
    - Medical Education. North Carolina 1971 (Box 63)
    - National Health Council 1967 (Box 63)
    - N.C. Comprehensive Health Planning Council 1968-1971 (Box 63)
    - N.C. Comprehensive Health Planning Project 1970 (Box 64)
    - N.C. Comprehensive Health Services 1968-1969 (Box 65)
    - N.C. Comprehensive Health Services, Financing 1969-1973 (Box 65)
    - Psychiatric Hospitals, North Carolina 1957, 1966-1967 (Box 63)
    - Smoking and Health 1969 (Box 63)
  - Race Problems: (Box 66)
    - Desegregation Plan, Durham School Board 1965 (Box 66)
    - Durham Negro Grievances. School Integration 1967-1969 (Box 66)
    - Durham Plan. Race Relations 1963 (Box 66)
    - National Commission on Civil Order. Riot Report 1968 (Box 66)
    - Segregation. Articles, etc. 1954-1969 (Box 66)
    - Segregation. Richmond, Va. Newspaper Clippings 1955 (Box 66)
  - Salem Academy (See N.C. Salem Academy) (Box 66)
  - Salvation Army. Cases from Social Services Department n. d. (Box 67)
  - Southern Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation. Seminars for Southern Journalists (See Press Associations) (Box 67)
  - Southern Regional Education Board. Seminars for Southern Journalists (See Press Associations) (Box 67)
  - State and Local Revenue Potential. Southern Regional Education Board 1969 (Box 67)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. National Policy and Performance Council 1968-1972 (Box 68)
  - University of North Carolina: (Box 68)
    - Black Student Movement 1968 (Box 68)
    - Election of Trustees 1966 (Box 68)
    - Installation of Chancellor Nelson E. Taylor 1972 (Box 68)
    - Newsletter 1970-1973 (Box 68)
  - Virginia Historical Society 1967 (Box 68)
  - Addition (87-94), 1976 (Box 70)
    Contains correspondence, notes and printed material for the development of Durham and its commemoration of the U.S. Bicentennial, 1976. Also contains information concerning health care in N.C., and notes from various conferences held by the U.S. State department for news editors.